最常见的几何类型称为欧几里德几何，它的名字命名为
The most common type of Geometry is known as Euclidean Geometry and it’s named after
亚历山大的Euclid和他是希腊人，很久以前就住在埃及。
Euclid of Alexandria and he was a Greek who lived a long time ago in Egypt.
公元前300年左右，他写了一本非常非常着名的书。实际上，一套13本书。它被称为The
Around 300 BC, he wrote a very, very famous book. In fact, a set of 13 books. It was called The
元素。而且，这是你在学校时学到的几何学的基础。
Elements. And, this is the basis of the Geometry that you learned when you were at school.
它是平面中物体的几何形状和三维空间中的物体。它的
It’s the Geometry of things in a plane and of things in three-dimensional space. It’s
关于线条，三角形和圆形的几何图形。如果你愿意的话，它基于一些公理
Geometry about lines and triangles and circles. It’s based on a few axioms, if you like
基本原则。而且，从这几个公理，所有其他原则
fundamental underlying principles. And, from these few axioms, all the other principles
可以导出几何。重要的是，欧几里德几何中没有数字。我们有
of Geometry can be derived. Importantly, there are no numbers in Euclidean Geometry. We have
线。我们有来信。我们谈论平行线，我们谈论直角，但是
lines. We have letters. We talk about parallel lines and we talk about right angles, but
欧几里德几何中没有数字，也没有坐标框架。
there are no numbers in Euclidean Geometry and there are no coordinate frames either.
勒内·笛卡尔（ReneDescartes）是17世纪非常着名的思想家。他是一位哲学家。
Rene Descartes was a very, very famous thinker in the 17th Century. He was a philosopher.
他是一名数学家，在他年轻的时候甚至是兼职雇佣兵。他是
He was a mathematician and he was even a part time mercenary in his younger days. He’s
他经常被称为现代哲学之父，他特别出名
often referred to as the Father of Modern Philosophy and he was particularly famous
对于这句话的原始拉丁语的翻译，“我想，因此我是。”
for the translation from the original Latin of this quote, “I think, therefore I am.”
关于笛卡尔的生活有很多故事。我特别喜欢的是
There are many stories about Descartes’ life. One that I particularly like is the
事实上，他发现整个上午躺在床上非常非常有用
fact that he found that was very, very useful to lay in bed all through the morning and
认为。这是他的思考时间。而且，这是一个非常好的原则。
think. It was his thinking time. And, it’s a really great principle.
一天早上，他躺在床上，看着墙壁，一只苍蝇进来了，它降落了
One morning, he was lying in bed, looking at the wall, and a fly came in, and it landed
在墙壁上。并且，他意识到他将能够描述苍蝇的位置
on the wall. And, he realized that he would be able to describe the position of the fly
仅仅是两个数字。因此，无论苍蝇在墙上的哪个地方，都可以进行描述
simply in terms of two numbers. So wherever the fly was on the wall, it could be described
非常简洁地使用两个数字。而且，这是笛卡尔坐标的基础
very succinctly using just two numbers. And, this is the basis of the Cartesian coordinate
框架，我们用两个坐标，两个数字表示平面中某物的位置。
frame where we represent the position of something in the plane using two coordinates, two numbers.
因此，笛卡尔所做的非常重要的事情是他将代数添加到欧几里德几何中。
So, the very important thing that Descartes did was he added Algebra to Euclidean Geometry.
而且，这使我们可以用方程表达形状。我们可以表达线条
And, that allowed us then to express shapes in terms of equations. We can express lines
在等式方面。我们有两条线的方程。我们可以弄清楚它们是如何相交的
in terms of equation. We have the equations for two lines. We can work out how they intersect
和它们相交的角度。它是代数与古代几何的融合。
and what angle they intersect. It’s the fusion of Algebra with the ancient Geometry.
我们将其称为笛卡尔几何或解析几何。它被称为笛卡儿。
We refer to this as Cartesian Geometry or Analytic Geometry. It’s called Cartesian.
这源于他在拉丁语中的名字Cartesius。所以，他就是那个发达的人
That’s derived from his name in Latin which was Cartesius. So, he is the one who developed
坐标系，这是我们今天非常非常熟悉的概念，但它可以追溯到
the coordinate system, a very, very familiar concept to us today, but it dates back to
只有17世纪。那么，让我们看一下2D坐标系。我们有一对轴。
only the 17th Century. So, let’s look at a 2D coordinate frame. We have a pair of axes.
这些中的每一个都是一个实数行，它们在我们称之为的点相交
Each of these is a real number line and they intersect at a point that we refer to as the
起源。因此，两个轴形成2D坐标系，x轴和y轴。现在，我们来吧
origin. So, two axes form a 2D coordinate frame, an x-axis and a y-axis. Now, let’s
用这个二维坐标系描述一个点。为了做到这一点，我们
describe a point using this two-dimensional coordinate frame. In order to do that, we
将一条线向下放到x轴，它与原点的距离由数量引用
drop a line down to the x-axis and its distance from the origin we refer to by the quantity
一个。并且，我们将另一条线移到y轴和沿y轴的距离
a. And, we drop another line across to the y-axis and the distance along the y-axis from
原点我们称之为距离b。因此，可以非常简洁地描述P点
the origin we refer to as the distance b. So, the point P can be described very succinctly
使用一对数字，我们将它们写在括号中就像那样。
using a pair of numbers and we write them in brackets just like that.
数学家会说一个点是n维空间中的一个位置。我们会
A mathematician would say that a point is a location in an n-dimensional space. We would
说P点是实数的一个元素，或者属于一个实数的一个元素
say that the point P is an element of, or belongs to, the set of real numbers to the power of
ñ。在这种情况下，它将是R平方。我们可以用笛卡尔坐标表示这一点。
n. In this case, it would be R squared. We can represent the point by a Cartesian coordinate.
我们也可以将它称为n元组。这是一组n个数字。我们给他们编号
We can also refer to it as an n-tuple. That’s a group of n numbers. We number them from
x1，x2，一直到xn。同样，在简单的二维情况下，n简单地相等
x1, x2, all the way up to xn. Again, in the simple two-dimensional case, n is simply equal
我们可以将矢量视为从坐标系原点到箭头的箭头
to 2. We can think of a vector as an arrow from the origin of our coordinate frame to
兴趣点。并且，我们用小写字母表示向量。按大写分
the point of interest. And, we denote vectors by lower case letters. Points by upper case
字母，小写字母矢量。在这种情况下，小写p。
letters, vectors by lower case letters. In this case, lower case p.
向量有两个组件。长度为a的水平分量和垂直分量
A vector has got two components. A horizontal component of length a, and a vertical component
长度b。我们写矢量p与我们写点P的方式不同。我们写
of length b. We write the vector p differently to the way we write the point P. We write
它作为一个矢量。这是一堆数字，一个在另一个之上。在这种情况下，一个以上
it as a vector. That’s a stack of numbers, one above the other. In this case, a above
湾所以，它是一个双元素向量。它也与2×1矩阵相同。
b. So, it’s a two element vector. It’s also the same as a 2 by 1 matrix.
这是一个有两行一列的矩阵。
That’s a matrix with two rows and one column.
数学家会说矢量是一个元素
A mathematician would say that a vector is an element of an
n维向量空间，我们写下，因为小写p是元素或属于
n-dimensional vector space and we'd write that as lower case p is an element of or belongs
到n的幂的实数集合。再次，在这个简单的情况下，n是相等的
to the set of real numbers to the power of n. Once again, in this simple case, n is equal
到2，因为它是一个二维坐标系。我们可以代表我们的向量，我们的箭头
to 2 because it’s a two-dimensional coordinate frame. We can represent our vector, our arrow
在坐标系上，作为数学n向量，具有两个元素的向量。和
on the coordinate frame, as a mathematical n vector, a vector with two elements. And
所以，这是元素x1，x2，一直到xn，我们应用转置运算符。
so, that’s the elements x1, x2, all the way up to xn and we apply the transpose operator.
在这里，我把矢量写成行向量。元素水平地彼此相邻。
Here, I’ve written the vector as a row vector. The elements are next to each other horizontally.
当我转置它时，它变成一个列向量，元素一个在另一个之上，并且这个
When I transpose it, it becomes a column vector, the elements one above the other, and this
当我们开始将矩阵和向量相乘时，它将变得很重要。
will become important later, when we start to multiply matrices and vectors together.
我们还可以认为向量是相对位移。它谈到一项动议。怎么样
We can also consider that a vector is a relative displacement. It talks about a motion. How
我们从起源到点P？我们怎么去那里？好吧，我们遵循这条道路
do we get from the origin to the point P? How do we get there? Well, we follow the path
这是这个向量，这个箭头。另一个重要的考虑因素是这个向量
which is this vector, this arrow. Another important consideration is that this vector
有一个特定的起点。因此，我们将其称为绑定向量。所以这
has a particular starting point. And so, we refer to this as a bound vector. So, this
这里用红色显示的向量与此向量不同。虽然他们也一样
vector here shown in red is different to this vector here. Although they’ve got the same
长度和它们有相同的角度，它们是不同的向量。重要的是留在
length and they’ve got the same angle, they are different vectors. Important to keep in
请记住，在这个过程中，我们所有的载体都受到约束。他们有一个特别的开始
mind that in this course, all of our vectors are bound. They have a particular starting
点。它们是根据特定坐标系定义的。
point. They’re defined with respect to a particular coordinate frame.
我们可以表达该向量的另一种方式，即小写p，就单位向量而言。那么我们
Another way we can express this vector, lower case p, is in terms of unit vectors. So, let’s
定义两个单位向量。这些是长度为1的向量，I表示具有长度的向量
define two unit vectors. These are vectors with a length of 1 and I denote those with
顶部的帽子符号。所以，我们有单位向量xhat和单位向量yhat。现在，
a hat symbol on top. So, we have the unit vector x hat and the unit vector y hat. Now,
我可以用两个组件来表达我的向量。一个分量是距离乘以
I can express my vector in terms of two components. One component is the distance a multiplied
通过单位向量xhat，再加上另一个向量，一个垂直向量，即距离b
by the unit vector x hat, plus another vector, a vertical vector, which is the distance b
乘以单位矢量yhat。所以，这是向量的组件表示
multiplied by the unit vector y hat. So, this is a component representation of a vector
我们将在本讲座中稍后使用这种表示法。
and we’ll be using this notation later on in this lecture.
重要的是，点和向量是不同的东西。点定义位置。我们做不到
Importantly, points and vectors are different things. A point defines a location. We can’t
一起加两点。这没有道理。而且，我们也不能增加两点。它的
add two points together. It makes no sense. And, neither can we multiply two points. It’s
一个毫无意义的概念。矢量不定义位置。他们指定如何从一个
a meaningless concept. Vectors don’t define a location. They specify how to get from one
位置到另一个。向量是我们可以添加的东西，我们可以减去。而且，我们可以
location to another. Vectors are things that we can add and we can subtract. And, we can
将矢量乘以标量。我可以有一个矢量;我可以将它乘以2.现在，我
multiply a vector by a scalar. I can have a vector; I could multiply it by 2. Now, I
有一个箭头，它的长度是两倍，但方向相同且开头相同
have an arrow that’s twice as long but in the same direction and with the same beginning
作为我以前的载体。两点之间的差异是矢量。所以，我可以
as the vector that I had before. The difference between two points is a vector. So, I can
取两点之间的差异，结果不再是一个点，结果
take the difference between two points and the result is no longer a point, the result
现在是一个载体。而且，类似地，我可以根据矢量位移定义一个点
is now a vector. And, similarly, I can define a point in terms of a vector displacement
从最初的角度来看。因此对于二维情况，一个点由两个实数表示
from an initial point. So for the two-dimensional case, a point is represented by two real numbers
并且矢量也由两个实数表示。但是，点和向量是不同的
and a vector is also represented by two real numbers. But, points and vectors are different
的东西。我们在创建坐标时需要小心
things. We need to be careful when we create a coordinate
帧。这是标准方式。它被称为右手坐标系。和，
frame. This is the standard way. It’s referred to as a right-handed coordinate frame. And,
我们从x轴摆动90度直到y轴。而且，这是另一个例子
we swing from the x-axis through 90 degrees up to the y-axis. And, here is another example
右手坐标系。如果我们将框架倒置，我们现在
of a right-handed coordinate frame. If we were to flip the frame upside down, we now
x轴在此方向，y轴向下。所以，我们将在90年代
have the x-axis in this direction and the y-axis down. So, we would swing this in 90
向下倾斜以定义y轴。现在，我们需要非常一致
degrees downwards in order to define the y-axis. Now, we need to be very consistent in the
我们定义坐标框架的方式，我们总是会使用右手坐标
way we define the coordinate frames and we’re always going to use a right-handed coordinate
帧。我们永远不会使用这样的坐标框架，只有这样的框架。
frame. We will never use a coordinate frame like this, only frames that look like this.
当我们从两个轴构造二维坐标系时，实际上有两个
When we construct a two-dimensional coordinate frame from two axes, there are in fact two
我们可以用不同的方式构建坐标系。一个所谓的左撇子
different ways that we can construct that coordinate frame. A so called left-handed
坐标框架和右手坐标框架。现在，在这个过程中，我们只会去
coordinate frame and a right-handed coordinate frame. Now, in this course, we’re only going
处理右手坐标系。那么，我们如何构建一个右手坐标
to deal with right-handed coordinate frames. So, how do we construct a right-handed coordinate
帧？好吧，我们首先绘制x轴，然后通过摆动创建y轴
frame? Well, we start by drawing the x-axis first and the y-axis is created by swinging
x轴逆时针方向90度。这给了我们一个右手坐标
the x-axis 90 degrees in the counterclockwise direction. That gives us a right-handed coordinate
帧。所以，无论坐标框架的方向是什么，相对方向
frame. So, no matter what the orientation of the coordinate frame, the relative orientation
x和y轴非常关键，它必须遵循这个惯例。另一个重要
of the x and y axes is really critical and it must follow this convention. Another important
要记住的是欧几里德几何只适用于飞机。而且，欧几里得之一
thing to keep in mind is that Euclidean Geometry only applies to planes. And, one of Euclid’s
假设或公理对此非常非常清楚，那就是平行线永远不会
postulates or axioms is very, very clear about this, and that is that parallel lines never
相交，当然，就是在飞机上的情况。
intersect and that is, of course, the case on a plane.
然而，在诸如球体之类的东西上，例如，我们星球的表面，这不再是
However, on something like sphere, for instance, the surface of our planet, this no longer
是的。赤道上的平行线将在两极交叉。的规则
holds true. Parallel lines at the equator will intersect at the poles. The rules of
欧几里德几何不适用于这样的表面，但我们会说表面
Euclidean Geometry do not apply on such a surface, but we would say that the surface
地球导致非欧几里德几何。然而，在一个小区域，欧几里德
of the Earth leads to a non-Euclidean Geometry. However, over a small area, the Euclidean
几何是一个非常好的近似。所以，在一个房间的规模，甚至可能甚至结束
Geometry is a very good approximation. So, over the scale of a room, maybe even over
城市规模，欧几里德几何-平行线不相交的事实
the scale of a city, Euclidean Geometry - the fact that parallel lines don’t intersect
-是一个很好的假设。
- is a pretty good assumption to make.